Guide to the James Lockwood Wright papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
James Lockwood Wright papers
1828-1858
MS 1078
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
The papers consist of eleven volumes of a journal kept by Wright from his first years at Yale College in 1828. While there he reports on a lecture by Elias Boudinot on behalf of the Cherokee nation and various temperance and abolition activities. The journals are chiefly devoted to religious meditations and describe the various revival movements of his era and his evangelical work with black residents of New Haven. He also records various aspects of his personal life including five mental breakdowns between 1828 and 1853, his family's health, and gives an account of the birth of his fourth child. The journals also include transcriptions of his sermons as well as those by others. With the papers is a letter from James Heyden Wright to Marion Wright Messimer on the journal.
Wright, James Lockwood, 1810-1871
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated to Yale University by Marion Messimer in 1948.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers of James Lockwood Wright consist of an eleven volume journal kept for thirty years, from the beginning of his study at Yale College in 1828 through 1858. While Wright does describe various events in his life and the world around him, his major concern in with his inner religious condition. As a young man he constantly doubted the sincerity of his faith and his fitness for the ministry, and lamented his frequent lapses from Godly behavior and recurrent fits of depression (1828 Nov 29, Dec 20, 1831 Mar 14, 1835 Feb 1, 1842 Mar, 1853 Oct 15). Much interested in the revival movements of his era, he participated both as a student and as a minister (1831 Mar 14, 1833 Sep, 1851 Jan 27, 31, 1858 Jan 27), and describes evangelical work with black residents of New Haven (1833 Feb 3), the process of conversion of one of his parishioners (1851 Jan 31), and a multitude of sermons, both his own and others.
Other topics which Wright mentions include his activities as a Yale student, including attendance at a lecture by Elias Boudinot on behalf of the Cherokee nation (1832 Feb 14) and various temperance and abolition activities (1833 Sep 3). After graduation Wright lived by farming, teaching school, and occasional preaching before taking a full-time position as minister, first in Burlington, Connecticut, in 1848, and then in Haddam, Connecticut, in 1855. His journal briefly records his activities along with notes on slavery (1841 Oct 22, 1850 Mar-Apr), local politics (1850 Mar-Apr), and his own and his family's health. He describes in some detail a bout of illness apparently combined with some sort of mental breakdown which he suffered (1853 Oct 15), and provides a lengthy account of the birth of his fourth child, in preparation for which his wife underwent a series of water treatments and a diet of graham bread.
In addition to the journal, this collection contains a letter from James Heyden Wright to Marion (Wright) Messimer concerning the journal.
African Americans -- Religion; Cherokee Indians; Childbirth; Depression, Mental; Education; Evangelicalism -- Connecticut; Mental illness; Religious thought -- 19th century; Temperance; Connecticut; Diaries; Sermons; Clergy; Wright, James Heyden; Wright, James Lockwood, 1810-1871; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1832; Yale University -- Students
- Original accession
  - Letter of James Heyden Wright to Marion Messimer, 1936 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Journals
    - 1828 Nov 26 -1833 Apr·8 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1832 Oct 31 -1833 Dec 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1833 Sep 3 -30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1833 Dec 25 -1835 Aug 27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1835 Dec 28-1841 Jun 8, 1842 Mar (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1840 -1843 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1843 Apr 13 -May 12 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1845 Dec 6 -1849 Nov 28 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1849 Nov 30 -1851 Nov 7 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1852 Jan -1857 Jan 10 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1852 Jan 12 -1858 Mar 24 (Box 1, Folder 12)